npower.com 2019-12-27

# Privacy policy | About us | npower

We can only use your personal information where that is permitted by data protection laws. Those laws require that where we use your personal information we must satisfy one condition (legal basis) for processing. The legal bases are consent, to comply with our legal obligations, to perform a contract, if it’s in our legitimate interests and for special category data (health) it is in your vital interests.

Set out below are the different legal bases and the types of processing we carry out:

### Legal basis for processing

#### Consent

Where you have provided consent we will rely on that to process your information for the purposes set out at the time that the request for consent was made.

You can change that consent at any time (either by withdrawing it or giving your consent where you previously hadn’t). The consequence of withdrawing your consent might be that we are no longer able to do certain things for you.

See the section on “Your rights relating to the personal information we hold about you” then “Right to withdraw consent”.

#### Processing activities (purposes)

##### Cookies

We use cookies on our website/App to collect information about the device you use to access our website or App or sometimes third parties collect that on our behalf.

You are asked to do this before using our website/App. If you refuse consent or you later remove it you may affect our ability to provide the services you want.

See our cookie policy for more information.

##### Marketing

To provide you with marketing information (including by phone, text message, email, via your online account and via your Smart in home display) about products and services (including third party products and services) which we think may benefit you in your everyday lives (if you have agreed to receive such information).We ask for consent when you sign up with us but you can change your mind at any time.

##### Market research

We may ask you to participate in market research (such as surveys, participation in focus groups etc.) to help improve the way we provide our services and products that we are able to make available to you – if you agree your feedback is given with your consent.  

##### Smart meter half hourly energy use

If you have a Smart meter installed at your property, we will only collect details of your half-hourly energy usage if you have given us your consent to do so.  

##### You agree to the disclosure

If you request us to disclose your personal data to other people or organisations such as to a relative to deal with your account on your behalf or to a person or organisation who has agreed to pay your bills or to company dealing with a claim on your behalf or you otherwise agree to such disclosures (for example to a charity providing you with debt assistance).

When we process any special categories of personal information at your request (e.g. your racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, trade union membership, genetic data, biometric data, data concerning your health, sex life or sexual orientation).

##### Priority Services

If you elect to either go on our Priority Services Register (which is a set of services that may be available to you or to people who may be living with you where, due to your (or their) health, age or some temporary reason (for example a bereavement) additional assistance may be required) or you agree for us to record details of your health etc. (information about your circumstances) we need your consent to do so.

If you consent we will use that information to assist us in providing the priority services you have requested (if any), managing your account so we are aware you may need additional help and support (for example having a bespoke debt pathway), for internal performance review, analysis, reporting and audit purposes (both internally and to report to Ofgem) to ensure our compliance with our obligations and to improve our services to you. We may share your information about your circumstances with with agents and service providers (like metering companies) who carry out services on our behalf.

If you agree we may also share your information with energy distributors and transporters (who may then share that information with water companies in line with agreed industry processes) so they can tailor their services to help you e.g. if there is a loss of power or water supply.

### Legal basis for processing

#### Vital interests

We may need to share information about your circumstances with third parties because we believe you or someone else’s life is in imminent danger.

This will be assessed on an individual basis and we will not share information unless we really believe there is a serious risk.

#### Processing activity (purposes)

Whether or not you are registered on PSR referred to above if you are in danger of being cut off and we believe you may need extra help we may record information about your circumstances.

You or a member of your household may need this extra help as a result of your (or their) health, age, disability or financial circumstances (we assess and record who may require extra help as a result of their circumstances) to assist you or them and ensure you or they stay on supply.  

### Legal basis for processing

#### Performance of our contract with you to provide products and services or to take steps at your request prior to entering into that contract

The information described above will be provided to us by you because you want to engage with us or take our products and services.

Our use of your information will be governed by your contract terms. It is up to you if you provide it but if you do not it may affect the products and services you want.

#### Processing activity (purposes)

  * To provide you with a quote (which may include making an assessment of your credit worthiness by automated decision making to decide which products and services and payment methods are most suitable for you).
  * To help us identify you so we know who we are talking to and authenticate the information you provide for security purposes. We may check against information we already hold about you as an energy supplier and potentially publicly available information such as social media.
  * To set up and manage your account including processing and collecting payments, recovering debts, analysing your account history and improving our service to you.
  * Sending you service messages such as account notifications and communications such as price and other terms and conditions changes.
  * To supply you with any products or services you have asked us for such as the supply of gas or electricity (or both), which may include passing your details on to third parties and partnerships to fulfil offers or cashback to you.
  * To enable you to access our website or App (including your online account if you have one) to use our services.
  * To set you up in the appropriate industry systems based on agreed industry processes when you change your supply to or away from us including obtaining meter reads, resolving metering disputes etc.
  * To measure your gas or electricity use (or both) and to work out your bills.
  * To assess health and safety, environmental and financial risks to you.
  * To provide and improve customer support.
  * To resolve complaints and query resolution.
  * To train our staff and monitor our services. This may involve us recording our conversations with you or keeping copies of our correspondence with you to make sure we are providing you with a good service and are keeping to our legal and regulatory obligations.

### Legal basis for processing

#### As necessary to fulfil a legal obligation

This is where we are required to do something by law, regulatory requirement or by way of a court order.

#### Processing activity (purposes)

  * To run our business in an efficient and proper way. This includes managing our financial position, business capability, planning, communications, corporate governance, and audit.
  * To help prevent and detect debt, theft, fraud or loss of gas or electricity (or both) including preparing and sending reports to the entity contracted to run the Theft Risk Assessment Service. See the section headed “Theft and Fraud Prevention”.
  * To comply with legal and regulatory requirements including those set out in the relevant gas and electricity Acts, our licence conditions and industry codes which govern how we operate.
  * To comply with orders made by the Court where we may be required to disclose information about you.
  * To provide certain information to Ofgem as regulator for the energy industry either as part of an investigation by them or as part of request for information or as part of an audit of our services.
  * If you have a Green Deal plan to manage the collection of the monies you owe to the relevant Green Deal provider and to update the industry parties and industry database as appropriate in line with agreed industry processes.
  * For demand forecasting and settlement in so far as is required to meet our industry requirements.
  * To relevant law enforcement agencies or government agencies where we have been asked to provide the information for legal or regulatory reasons (if we receive a legitimate request for the information).
  * To assist you if you exercise your legal rights under data protection law.
  * For the establishment and defence of legal rights.
  * To verify your identity, make credit fraud prevention and anti-money laundering checks.

### Legal basis for processing

#### As necessary for our own legitimate interests

This is where we use your personal information for our normal business purposes where the benefits of doing so are not outweighed by your fundamental rights or freedoms.

You have a right to object to this type of processing. See the section on “Your rights relating to the personal information we hold about you” then “Right to object”.

#### Processing activity (purposes)

  * To run our business in an efficient and proper way. This includes managing our financial position, business capability, planning, communications, corporate governance, and audit.
  * To help prevent and detect crime such as fraud and money laundering where this is not covered by our legal requirements and we are processing your personal information to help reduce the cost of this activity being spread across all customers by way of increased prices.
  * To contact you with service messages that are not strictly necessary for the performance of our contract but we believe will assist you and will improve our service to you unless in each case (with the exception of service messages or online notifications via your online account (if you have one) which you are required to receive as part of having an online account), you tell us you do not wish to receive such service messages, notifications and communications by those means and you are not required to receive them as part of the product and/or services you have signed up to.
  * To use your information for marketing purposes so for example we can see what products and services may be of interest to you.
  * To provide you with advertising about our products and services which we think may benefit you in your everyday lives, using the internet and digital media technologies provided by third parties such as Facebook and Google. You can opt out of such marketing purposes by changing your settings on Facebook or Google or by contacting us.
  * To assist in debt prevention and debt recovery which may include tracing where you have moved to and identifying who is responsible for taking supply where such processes go beyond what is strictly necessary for the performance of our contract with you.
  * For demand forecasting and settlement to assist us in purchasing energy more efficiently.
  * To resolve complaints and query resolution which go beyond strictly performing our contract with you.
  * To carry out credit checks or otherwise assessing your credit worthiness.
  * To carry out performance reviews, monitoring, modelling and analysis, reporting, profiling, auditing, market research (where the analysis is carried out by third parties who do not provide us with your details unless we have your specific consent to do so and may extend beyond energy usage to include aspects of your lifestyle, payment history etc.) and statistical analysis to assist us in ensuring we can comply with legal and regulatory requirements (including those set out in our licence conditions and industry codes) as well as to help improve the way we provide our services and the products that we are able to make available to you.
  * To test systems to help improve the way we provide our services and the products that we are able to make available to you.
  * To monitor emails, calls, other communications, and activities on your account.
  * To carry out data enrichment to help us ensure the information we hold about you is accurate and up to date and to assist us in being able to contact you (which may involve purchasing data from someone else like a data broker or using publicly available sources like the Land Registry or the electoral register).
  * To take contact information like phone numbers or email addresses that are held on our internal systems e.g. Call Line Identification (used when you call in to us), Tallyman (used in the debt collection process) or Once (used in the complaints process) to carry out an internal data quality exercise where we will consolidate that information and (where validated) add it to your main customer account to ensure that we hold accurate and consistent information about you to assist in contacting you in relation to your account.
  * To report to and pay our referral partners such as telesales and broker websites like uswitch.
  * Web analytics to analyse and better configure our website and App.
  * To take part in government or industry initiatives (for example to tackle fuel poverty, improve energy efficiency or other social or consumer interests).
  * Whether or not you are registered on PSR referred to above if you are in danger of being cut off or we believe you (or someone who lives with you) may need extra help we may record a generic vulnerable marker (not going into any specific details about you or them).
  * You or a member of your household may need this extra help as a result of your (or their) health, age, disability or financial circumstances (we assess and record who may require extra help as a result of their circumstances) to assist you o or them and ensure you or they stay on supply.
  * We will use it to assist us in providing the priority services you have requested (if any), managing your account so we are aware you may need additional help and support (for example having a bespoke debt pathway), for internal performance review, analysis, reporting and audit purposes (both internally and to report to Ofgem) to ensure our compliance with our obligations and to improve our services to you.
  * We may share information about your circumstances with agents and service providers (like metering companies) who carry out services on our behalf. We may also share the fact you are potentially vulnerable (providing no special category data) with industry organisations like transporters and distribution network operators (who may then share that information with water companies in line with agreed industry processes) so that they are aware you may need additional assistance and can offer you appropriate services in case, for example, of a loss of power or water supply.  

  * If you have a display unit with your Smart meter, we may send messages (for example, general energy-efficiency messages) direct to it, unless you let us know at any time that you do not want to receive such information.
  * If you have a Smart meter to record your daily Smart meter energy use unless you have told us otherwise (see the section on “Use of Smart energy data” below).
